A Guide to the Claude H. Barlow Papers FA037
Rockefeller Archive Center
Claude H. Barlow papers
1919-1964
Rockefeller Archive Center
Barlow, Claude H.
FA037
4 Cubic Feet 8 document cases
Arrangement note
The collection comprises seven series:
Series 1 - Correspondence
Series 2 - Articles
Series 3 - Notes and Research Data
Series 4 - Reports
Series 5 - Reprints
Series 6 - Maps
Series 1053 - Photographs
Biographical/Historical note
Claude H. Barlow (1876-1969) was born in Lyons, Michigan. In his youth he learned a variety of crafts and arts, including metal working, woodworking, and painting, which he later used in scientific research and illustration.
Dr. Barlow attended the University of Michigan from 1899 to 1902 and received an M.D. degree from Northwestern in 1906.
Joining the American Baptist Foreign Mission Society in 1908, Dr. Barlow began twenty years of service as a medical missionary in China. He was Customs Medical Officer for the Chinese Maritime Customs in Ningpo, for which his fees went to the hospital; he was also a surgeon and hospital superintendent in Shaosing. Dr. Barlow received a China Medical Board fellowship to study the human intestinal fluke, which led to a Sc.D. from Johns Hopkins in 1929.
In 1929, Dr. Barlow joined the staff of the International Health Division and was sent to Egypt where he conducted hookworm and schistosomiasis campaigns and did basic snail research. In 1944 he infected himself with schistosomiasis in order to bring viable eggs to Johns Hopkins for study.
With the outbreak of World War II, the foundation terminated its Egyptian program and Dr. Barlow joined the Egyptian Ministry of Health, where he remained until his retirement in 1951. In 1951, he conducted a snail survey for South Africa and then returned to the United States.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) or audiovisual material (audio cassettes, VHS, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Scope and Contents note
The Claude H. Barlow collection covers the period from 1919 to 1964. Important subjects covered in this collection are: Bilharzia Snail Destruction Section; canal clearance; hookworm; sanitation; schistosomiasis; self-infection with schistosomiasis, fluke; snail research and studies; Fluke; and copper sulphate.
Among the correspondents are: M. Abdel Azim, C. H. Barlow, W. W. Cort, Ernest Faust, J. H. Franklin, R. W. Hegner, Victor G. Heiser, R. T. Hegner, Victor G. Heiser, R. T. Leiper, James Maxwell, Henry Meleney, J. Allen Scott, Norman R. Stoll, Horace Stunkard, W. H. Wright, and Charles Young.
File Plan note
Former Classification: IV 2A 12
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The papers of Claude H. Barlow were deposited with the Rockefeller Foundation Archives as an unrestricted gift in March 1970 and June 1971 by Mrs. John McConnell.
Flatfishes; Sanitation; Copper sulfate; Prevention and health; Schistosomiasis; Diseases; Snails as carriers of disease; Snails; South Africa; Egypt; United States; Barlow, Claude H.; Heiser, Victor George; Faust, Ernest Carroll; Azim, M. Abdel; Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division; Hegner, Robert William; Cort, William W. (William Walter); Leiper, Robert Thompson; Franklin, James H.; Scott, J. Allen; Wright, Willard H.; Meleney, Henry Edmund; Stoll, Norman Rudolph; Stunkard, Horace W. (Horace Wesley); Young, Charles W.
- Correspondence, 1
  Arrangement note
  This series is arranged chronologically.
  - 1919-1924 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1925-1929 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 1930 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 1931 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 1932 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 1933-1934 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 1935-1938 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 1939 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 1940 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 1941 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - 1942-1945 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - 1946 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - 1947-1949 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - 1950-1964 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Articles, 2
  This series is arranged alphabetically by title.
  - "Anatomy of Bulinus Truncatus", n.d. (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - "Another Bit of Chinese Quackery Vindicated" (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - "Bilharzia", n.d. (Box 2, Folder 17)
    Scope and Contents note
    Reprinted from the "Egyptian Gazette," February 13-20, 1951.
  - "Bilharzia Work in China", n.d. (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - "Bilharzia Work in Egypt", n.d. (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - "Bilharzia, a World Scourge", n.d. (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - "The Bilharzia Snail Control Section", n.d. (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - "The Biology of Planorbis Boissyi and Bulinus Truncatus" (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - "The Effect of the 'Winter Closure' of Water upon Snails Involved in Schistosomiasis in Egypt", n.d. (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - "Environmental Studies for the Ezmet Gebel", n.d. (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - "Epidemiological Study of the Royal Estate, Ezbit el Khassa", n.d. (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - "Experimental Ingestion of the Ova of Fasciolopsis Buski; Also the Ingestion of Adult Fasciolopsis Buski for the Purpose of Artificial Infestation", n.d. (Box 2, Folder 26)
    Reprinted from the "Journal of Parasitology," September 1921.
  - "Is There Dermatitis in Egyptian Schistosomiasis?", n.d. (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - "Jasper, Especially Egyptian Banded Jasper, as an Art Medium" (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - "Life Cycle of Fasciolopsis Buski (Human) in China", n.d. (Box 2, Folder 29)
    Reprinted from the "China Medical Journal," June 1923.
  - "The Life Span and Monthly Mortality Rate of Bulinus Truncatus and Planorbis Boissyi, the Intermediate Hosts of Schistosomiasis in Egypt" (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - "Monthly Incidence of Infestation of Planorbis Boissyi with Larval Schistosoma Mansoni and Bulinus Contortus with Larval Schistosoma Haematorium" (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - "A New Method for Examining Urine for Helminth Eggs", n.d. (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - "On the Correct Nomenclature of Bilharzia", n.d. (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - "An Original Device for the Study of Animals in a Water Environment", n.d. (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - "A Preliminary Note on the Life History of Clonorchis Sinesis in Chekiang Province, China", n.d. (Box 2, Folder 35)
    Reprinted from the "American Journal of Hygiene," January 1924.
  - "Preliminary Report on the Development of Fasciolopsis Buski Ova", n.d. (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - "A Project for Working Out the Life History of Fasciolopsis Buski with the Aim of Eliminating Fasciolopsiniasis from China", n.d. (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - "A Reply to Professor Khalil's Article", n.d. (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - "Seasonal Incidence of Snail Infestation with Human Schistosomes in a Limited Area in Egypt", n.d. (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - "The Snail Hosts of the Human Schistosomes of Egypt", n.d. (Box 3, Folder 40)
    Copy of preface from Barlow book.
  - "Snail Ponds" (Box 3, Folder 41)
    Reprinted from "The Journal of Parasitology," October 1950.
  - "A Study of the Revival, After Drying, of the Snail Hosts of the Human Schistosomes of Egypt", n.d. (Box 3, Folder 42)
    Includes handwritten manuscript.
  - "A Suggested Surgical Method for Reducing the Oxygen Tension in the Lungs of Patients Suffering from Advanced Pulmonary Tuberculosis", n.d. (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - "Suggested Problems of Investigation on Snails and Cercariae" (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - "Technic of Collecting and Examining Specimens" (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - "A Theory of Egg-Deposition by Bilharzia Haematobia", n.d. (Box 3, Folder 46)
    Reprinted from "The Journal of Parasitology," April 1949.
  - "The Treatment of Fasciolopsiasis", n.d. (Box 3, Folder 47)
    Reprinted from "The China Medical Journal," March 1927.
  - "The Value of Canal Clearance in the Control of Schistosomiasis in Egypt", n.d. (Box 3, Folder 48)
    Includes charts and notes.
  - "A Voluntary Infection with Schistosoma Haematobium", n.d. (Box 3, Folder 49)
    Reprinted from "The American Journal of Tropical Medicine," January 1949.
  - Miscellaneous Manuscript, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 50)
- Notes and Research Data, 3
  This series contains charts, drawings, graphs, statistics, notes and diaries. Photographs have been removed to the photograph series.
  This series is arranged alphabetically by topic.
  - Notes, 1930-1932 (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - Notes, 1950-1951 (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - Bilharzia Snail Destruction Section, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - Clearance Experiment, 1931-1936 (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - Clippings, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 55)
  - Collection Data - Schistosome Incidence in Significant Snails, 1934 (Box 4, Folder 56)
  - Copper Sulphate (Use of in Water Supplies), n.d. (Box 4, Folder 57)
  - Daily Deposition of Schistosoma Haematorium Snails, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 58)
  - Echinostome Cercaria - Notes and Drawing, 1923 (Box 4, Folder 59)
  - El Marg Graphs, 1934-1935 (Box 4, Folder 60)
  - El Marg Revival Studies, 1935 (Box 4, Folder 61)
  - Environmental Studies - Burtus, Badrashein, River Nile, 1935 (Box 4, Folder 62)
  - Environmental Studies - El Marg, 1934 (Box 4, Folder 63)
  - Environmental Studies - El Marg, 1935 (Box 4, Folder 64)
  - Environmental Studies - El Marg, 1936 (Box 4, Folder 65)
  - Environmental Studies - Matawa, 1934-1935 (Box 4, Folder 66)
  - Environmental Studies - Sursock, 1935 (Box 4, Folder 67)
  - Fluke Studies, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 68)
    Handwritten notes, drawings and charts.
  - Miscellaneous Data, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 69)
  - Pathological Notes - Dr. Bateman, CMS Hospital, Cairo, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 70)
  - Personal, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 71)
    Includes government passes and calling cards.
  - Protozoology Drawings, 1929 (Box 5, Folder 72)
  - Self-Infection, 1944 (Box 5, Folder 73)
    Includes notebook detailing experiment, notes and charts.
  - Snail Collections, 1929-1932 (Box 5, Folder 74)
  - Snail Collections - Dakhia Oasis, 1930 (Box 5, Folder 75)
  - Snail Measurements and Snail Observations (Book) (Box 5, Folder 76)
  - Snail Survey - South Africa, 1951 (Box 5, Folder 77)
  - Source Material, 1931-1939 (Box 5, Folder 78)
  - Swimming Motion of Schistosomes, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 79)
  - Sudan Report, 1931 (Box 6, Folder 80)
- Reports, n.d.; 4
  - Annual Report - Egypt, Bilharzia Snail Destruction Section, 1942-1951 (Box 6, Folder 81)
  - Annual Report - Egypt Hookworm Studies, 1930-1931 (Box 6, Folder 82)
  - Annual Report - Egypt Hookworm Studies, 1932-1933 (Box 6, Folder 83)
  - Annual Report - Egypt Schistosomiasis Studies, 1931 (Box 6, Folder 84)
  - Annual Report - Egypt Schistosomiasis Studies, 1935 (Box 6, Folder 85)
  - Annual Report - Egypt Schistosomiasis Studies, 1936-1938 (Box 6, Folder 86)
  - Annual Report - Egypt Schistosomiasis Studies, 1939-1940 (Box 6, Folder 87)
  - Annual Report - Egypt Endemic Diseases Section, 1937 (Box 6, Folder 88)
  - Bilharzia Committee Minutes, 1939-1940 (Box 6, Folder 89)
  - Bilharzia Snail Control Section, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 90)
  - Peking Union Medical College, 1927 (Box 6, Folder 91)
    Confidential report on state of health in China.
  - Report on Experiments Carried Out by the State Domains Administration with the Object of Comparing the Effectiveness of Different Systems of Land Drainage (Box 7, Folder 92)
  - Report to the Undersecretary of Public Health on the Problem of Bilharzia Control in Egypt, 1928 (Box 7, Folder 93)
  - South African Council for Scientific and Industrial Research - Verbatim Report of Informal Meeting on Bilharzia, Held at Pretoria on 29th and 30th March, 1951 (Box 7, Folder 94)
- Reprints, n.d.; 5
  - Bibliography and Reprints (Box 7, Folder 95)
  - Reprints, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 96)
  - Reprints, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 97)
- Maps, n.d.; 6
  Conditions Governing Access
  Due to the oversize nature and potentially brittle condition of this material, special arrangements may be required in order to view materials. Individual items may be restricted due to preservation concerns.
- Claude H. Barlow photographs, 1053
  Barlow, Claude H.
  - Claude H. Barlow (Box 40, Folder 393)
  - China Fluke Study (Box 40, Folder 394)
  - Egypt (Box 40, Folder 395)
  - Egypt - Anti-Schistosomiasis Project (Box 41, Folder 396)
  - Egypt - Anti-Schistosomiasis Project (Box 41, Folder 397)
  - Egypt - Anti-Schistosomiasis Project (Box 41, Folder 398)
  - Egypt - Anti-Schistosomiasis Project (Box 41, Folder 399)
  - Egypt - Anti-Schistosomiasis Project (Box 41, Folder 400)
  - South African Snail Survey 1 (Box 41, Folder 401)
  - South African Snail Survey 2 (Box 41, Folder 402)
  - Claude H. Barlow (Box 41, Folder 403)